The strings are
The strings are
just like the backdid new
just like the backdid new
and that's the place
and that's the place
where we call stone walking.
where we call stone walking.
Yeah, you can follow
Yeah, you can follow
their walk using partright
their walk using partright
here on your channel.
here on your channel.
They won't accept
They won't accept
your cause,
your cause,
but,
but,
security means
security means
you just have
you just have
cheek
toобраз
good night friends
各位朋友晚安
I'm actually here to fight today.
今天我其實是來代打的
Because it turned out that Vice President Wang Fansheng was going to preside over the
因為原來應該是王范生副院長要來主持
But he just happened to be leaving the country.
不過他剛好應要出國去了
So let me, a layman, do this as the moderator
所以就請我這個外行人來做這個當主持人
Today we are very happy to have invited researcher Zhang Zhenghua
今天我們非常高興有邀請到張正華研究員
He's a researcher at our fish lab.
是我們食魚所的研究員
I just talked to him a little while ago and he has a very long history
我剛才跟他聊了一下他有非常悠久的歷史
All thirty years of researcher experience in Piscivora
在食魚所有三十幾年的研究員的經驗
Researcher Zhang is currently a researcher of our Central Research Institute
張研究員目前是我們中研的研究員
is also a researcher in archeology at our Center for Human Design
也是我們人設中心的考古學的研究員
About the CEO of Album Center
就專輯中心的執行長
He is also from the Department of Anthropology of Tsinghua University
他也是清華大學人類學系的
adjunct professor combined
兼任教授合併的
Dr. Zhang graduated from Harvard University
張博士是哈佛大學畢業的
just chatted
剛才聊了一下
I just found out when he was studying at Harvard
才知道他在哈佛念書的時候
I'm also building bridges
我也在建橋
This place in Maryland
這個馬州的地方
Although in the same city
雖然在同一個城市
But I didn't know much at that time
但是那時候不太認識
so happy now
所以現在很高興
I know Researcher Zhang also stayed at Harvard
我知道張研究員也在哈佛待過
Teacher Zhang's expertise
張老師的專長
in archaeology, of course
當然是在考古學方面
especially many recent
尤其是很多最近
Especially some archaeological ones under the waters
尤其在水域下面的一些考古的
This topic is very researched
這個議題非常有研究
His academic experience is very rich
他的學經歷非常的豐富
Then in our research
那麼在我們研究
He also served as the deputy director of domestic research institutes
在國內的研究院裡面也當過副所長
But he is the curator of the National Taiwan Museum of Prehistoric Culture
但是他是國立台灣史前文化研究館的館長
that one is in Taitung
那個在台東
i visited twice
我參觀過兩次
is a very nice place
是非常不錯的一個地方
Well, I also held many important positions in this National Science Council.
那麼也在這個國科會擔任過很多重要的職務
Now he is also the director of Anthropology and Ethnology
那現在也是人類學民族學的這個理事長
chairman of the society
學會的理事長
Chairman of the Chinese School Archeology Society
中華學校考古學會的理事長
International Indo-China
國際的Indo-China
The president of the Bhistory Association, etc.
Bhistory Association的president理事長等等
So this academic manager is indeed very rich
所以這個學經理的確是非常的豐富
Then I won the Contact Award from the National Science Council.
那麼也得過國科會的接觸獎
This Wu Sanlian award and so on
這個吳三連獎等等
so today we are happy
所以今天我們很高興
This can invite Dr. Zhang to come here
這個能夠請到張博士來這邊
Tell us about the test results in the Taiwan waters
替我們介紹一下這個台灣海域的考果
So today I'm here to host
那麼今天是我來主持
feast of knowledge
這個知識饗宴
Come to fill up once
來報滿的一次
I have presided over a lot of life sciences
我主持過的都是生命科學比較多
rarely fully booked
很少報滿
I am very happy to have a warm state today
今天非常高興有熱烈的狀況
So we can also expect
所以我們也可以期待
his speech is rich
他的演講很豐富
I heard he has 190 slides
聽說他有190張的slides
so we have an hour and a half
所以我們一個半鐘頭
see if he can finish
看看他能不能講得完
Less time to ask questions if you don't finish speaking
講不完就發問的時間就比較少一點
We please warmly welcome our teacher Zhang
我們請熱烈歡迎我們張老師
Vice President Wang
王副院長
And our colleagues in the hospital
還有我們本院的同事同仁
and my friends
還有各位的朋友
Goodnight everybody
大家晚安
I am honored today
我今天還榮幸
it's not an honor
其實不是榮幸
It's the courtyard that ordered me to speak
就是這個院裡面命令我來講
I had to give orders
我只好付出命令
let's make a report
我們來做一個報告
When I was asked to report
當初讓我報告的時候
I asked what topic I was talking about
我問我講什麼題目
I consider
我考慮
Actually, I personally study archaeology.
其實我個人是學考古的
In fact, there are many topics that can be discussed
其實可以講題目很多很多的
Because of archeology, our specialty is to go to the mountains and go to the sea.
因為考古我們特色就是上山下海
So there are quite a lot of different themes.
所以各種各樣的題材其實蠻多的
Later, I still chose this topic
後來我還是選了這個題目
Because this topic is what we have been doing in recent years
因為這個題目是最近這幾年我們在做
Moreover, it is actually a topic that has made substantial contributions to Taiwan.
而且對我們台灣其實也是有實質貢獻的一個題目
Because Taiwan is surrounded by sea
因為在台灣的四面環海
Taiwan is surrounded by sea
我們台灣四周環海
But in this field, there was actually a blank in the past.
但是在這個領域裡面其實過去一片空白
almost blank
幾乎是空白的
So we compare these countries around us
所以我們比起我們周圍的這些國家
In fact, a lot behind
其實落後了很多
Our surroundings are like mainland Japan
我們這個周圍的像日本大陸
Shenger Philippines in Southeast Asia Vietnam in Thailand
盛爾東南亞的菲律賓 越南的泰國
They've done a lot of this
他們這一方面都做了蠻多的
But our Taiwan is a blank
但是我們台灣是一片空白
None so it's a zero
都沒有 所以是個零
So in recent years this opportunity
所以最近幾年有這個機會
to take charge of such a job
來負責這樣一個工作
In fact, I personally feel terrified on the one hand.
其實我個人一方面感覺到很惶恐
On the other hand, I also feel that it is a sense of experimentation.
另外一方面也覺得是一個實驗感
I think
我覺得
The vice president of our company in Academia Sinica just said that I have a long history
我们在中研院的公司刚刚副院长说我有悠久的历史
So here I think it is necessary to make some contributions to the country.
那么所以在这边我觉得对国家多少还是要有点贡献吧
Otherwise, I'm just messing around here like that.
要不然的话在这边白混了那样子
So I just like to talk about this topic today
所以我就就像今天讲这个题目
I also want to share with all our guests
我也想和我们的所有的来宾
Can come to share some of our work in recent years
能够来分享我们这几年一些工作的
Some preliminary results
一些初步的一些成果
Well, of course, maybe our poster is too beautiful.
那么当然大概说不定我们这海报做得太漂亮了
So then we attract so much of our audience
所以后来我们吸引这么多的我们的听众
Ms. Huang, tell me the truth, give me an email saying
这个你说实的黄小姐给我一个email说
Wow, what is the full report this time?
哇这次是什么报满这样子
Then I said oh, I'm surprised
那我说哎呀我很意外啊
Because in the past, our archaeological topics were all very cold farts.
因为过去我们这个考古的题目都是很冷屁的啊
Then it is very difficult to have an audience for this audience.
那么这个听众是很难有听众的
Then I go to class and study again.
那我上课再学上课了
Probably the amount of inflation is two or three people or seven or eight people.
大概充气量就是两三个人或者七八个人这样子啊
Ah, so there are so many people saying 250 people, I was shocked again
啊所以这个这么多说250个人啊我又吓一跳
I'm also very glad that everyone is interested. Of course it's great.
我也很高兴大家有兴趣当然很好啊
so so so so not much time today
所以所以那所以今天时间不多
uh yes
呃是这样
I prepared a lot of slides like this
我准备了其实很多slides这样子
But I know time is unlimited
可是我知道时间没有限
So I deleted some
所以我删掉了一些
But I didn't notice that there are still so many
但是我没有注意到还是那么多
so i'll be soon
所以我等一下就很快的
See how much you can talk like this
看看能够讲多少就讲多少这样子
then this
那么这个
So this underwater archeology
那么这个水下考古
It's a word that sticks to this archeology
它是一个沾到这个考古的两个字
Therefore, in the common people's concept
所以一般的人的观念里面
In fact, archeology is digging in the ground.
其实考古就是在地上面挖
So just dig down
所以就是往下面挖
is archeology
就是考古
So the general idea is that terrestrial archaeology
所以一般观念都是陆地考古
So I seldom think of doing archaeology in waters
所以很少想到水域里去做考古
Well, so our archeology on land
那么所以我们这个在陆地考古
In fact, up to millions of years
其实可以上到几百万年
then until modern times
然后一直到近代
In fact, it is also a time when we do archaeology.
其实也都是我们做考古的一个时间的
a category
一个范畴
so like this
所以像这个
Everyone is a stereotype like these
像这些大家都是刻板印象
Those who go to archaeology are doing monuments.
这个去考古的都是要去做古蹟
Japan's this
日本的这个
some say
有些本人说
actually
实际上
Those people are reformers
那部分人都是改革
But it turns out to be a post
でも虽然是针像
then proof
然后是证明
And it's still kinda cool
而且还是有一点棒
That UNGYA special treasure
那UNGYA特宝
Anyway, look at it as a
反正把它看的是个
just started coming out like that
刚开始出来像那个
show scene
show 场面那种
a little small
有点小
kind of
那种
prepare for seat
照 seat 准备
to find
要找一下
will definitely come out later
以后一定会出来
promote can also
promote 还可以
From this next
从下这一件
this maya this mexican
这个马亚的这个墨西哥的
These Pyramids from Astic
Astic的这些Pyramid
and these things
还有这些东西
In fact, Huang's bima swims
其实黄的这个碧马泳
And these childlike, jade-like
还有这些童气啊 玉气啊
these things
这些东西
Well in fact
那么事实上
For the last forty or fifty years now
现在最近这个四五十年以来
In fact, now everyone is starting to notice
其实现在大家开始注意到
In fact, archeology is not just on the road
其实考古并不只是在路上面
actually in the water
其实在水里面
In fact, there are many, many
其实有很多很多的
Remnants of some human cultures
一些人类的文化的遗存
What about these remains?
那这些遗存呢
its quantity its value
它的数量 它的价值
Definitely not faster than on land
绝对不会迅于陆地上的
Although there are pyramids on land
陆地上虽然有金字塔
But there are also pyramids in the water
但水里也有金字塔
There are many precious things in the water
水里面有很多很珍贵的
of these cultures
这些文化的
remains of human culture
人类文化的遗存
its importance is very important
它重要性是非常重要的
And all the waters of the earth
而且整个地球的水域
take up our entire planet
占掉我们整个地球的
Three quarters of the earth is water
地球的四分之三都是水
Only a quarter of the land is occupied by land
陆地其实只占了四分之一
maritime
海上
In fact, so in the sea
其实所以在海里面
It can be said that it is a very colorful underwater world
可以说非常繽纷的水中世界
So the ocean it doesn't just have
所以海洋它不只是有
These are beautiful underwater style
这些很漂亮的海底的风格
Because of these coral reefs and so on
封光 由于这些珊瑚礁等等
In fact, there are still a considerable number of these human cultural relics in the sea.
其实海里面还有相当数量的这些人类的文化的遗存
Of course, on the one hand, some of these relics were deliberately left behind by humans.
当然这些遗存一方面有一些是人类刻意的丢下去的
Some are sunk into the sea due to the rise or change of the water level.
有一些是被水 海水面的上升或者是变化而沉降到海里面去的
Of course, some of them entered by accident.
当然也有一些是意外的进入的
Like a plane crash, the plane just fell into the sea, right?
像飞机空难 飞机就掉到海里去了 对不对
So there are actually a lot of these things in our sea area
所以这些东西其实是在我们的海域里面是非常多的
Then these things also need to do some archaeology
那这些东西它同样的需要去做一些考古
The so-called archeology is not an old treasure
所谓考古它就不是一个老宝
It is a scientific and systematic way to do some research and a collection
它是经过一个科学的 有系统的这样去做一些研究 一个搜集
So we actually have all kinds of relics of human culture from the sea
所以我们从海里面其实有各种各样的这样的人类的文化的遗存
Strange, this is a topic we are familiar with recently
奇怪 这个是我们最近很认门的这个题目
overall climate change
整個氣候的變遷
climate warming
氣候暖化
so one day
所以將來有一天
This scenario may arise
這種情景也許會出現
look at these cities now
你看這些現在的城市
Maybe in the sea in the future
將來說不定在海底
if one day in the future
這個將來如果有一天
It must be exciting to do underwater archaeology
去做水下考古的話一定很精彩
you see this is a
你看這個是一個
If the sea level rises two meters
假如海水面提高兩公尺
this is new york
這是紐約的
This is what a space in New York looks like
紐約的一個空間就變成這個樣子了
So it's not really impossible
所以這個其實並不是不可能的
In the future these so-called legacies of humanity
將來這些所謂的人類的遺產
These heritages that will become underwater in the future
將來變成水下的這些遺產
So underwater is actually a
所以水下其實是一個
Implicit responsibilities, let's do some discussion
含蓄的職責我們去做一些探討的地方
So in this underwater heritage
那麼在這個水下遺產裡面
In fact, there are various categories
其實有各種各樣的類別
I just said there are buildings
剛講過有建築物
city ​​with a past
有過去的城市
Carved castle with a past
有過去的雕堡
There are villages and towns
有村落城鎮
But there's a whole lot more
但是另外還有一大部分
what is p by boat
P是什么乘船
The number of boats is quite abundant
乘船数量相当相当的丰富
more than vietnam
越南多
This image is from Google Earth
这个图是从Google Earth上面的
each of these little blue dots
这些每一个这些小小的蓝色的点点
Just looking at the Earth from space
就是从太空上面看地球
The ruins of these boats that can be seen
可以看得见的这些乘船的遗迹
Of course, most of these boat rides are in shallow seas
当然这些乘船大部分在浅海
or near the sea
或者在靠近的海边
So it can be seen that this shipwreck
所以它看得见的这种乘船遗迹
after it marks it
它把它标示出来以后
you are everywhere
你到处都是
So this number can be said to be quite large
所以这个数量可以说是相当相当的庞大的
So of course there are more under the sea
所以在海底下当然更多了
can zoom in a bit
可以放大一点
you can look at these
可以看看这些
You see these are secret codes
你看这些都是秘密码
not just in the sea
不只是在海域
In land rivers and lakes
在陆域的河流湖泊里面
There are also many, many of these ancient boats
也有很多很多的这些古代的这些乘船
the most famous one by boat
最有名的一条乘船
Everybody knows
大家知道
Do you all know each other?
大家都认识吧
Titanic Anne
铁达安妮
At this time the most famous
这时候最有名的
The whole world probably talks about taking a boat
全世界大概讲乘船
don't even mention this one
都非要提到這一個
So what about the city ship after the silence of 1912
那麼這個城船在1912年沉默之後呢
Then it exists in the North Atlantic Ocean below 3000 meters
那麼存在這個3000公尺以下的這個北大西洋裡面
Then came 1985
那麼後來到1985年呢
It was only discovered by this man's chest
才被發現 就被這位人胸發現了
He came from this state of Massachusetts in the United States
他是在美國的這個麻州的物質後的
a physicist
一位物理學家
Then he invented this underwater submersible
那麼他發明了這個水下的這個潛航器
so go down in the water
所以下到水裡面去呢
To be able to capture this image of Titanic
才能夠拍攝到這個Titanic他的這個影像
Of course this is a very famous city ship
當然這個是一個非常有名的一條城船
Well, of course his value is being discussed a lot now
那麼當然他的價值現在有很多的討論
because he was 1912
因為他是1912年
His age is close to 100 years from now
他的年代距離現在接近100年
less than 100 years old
還不到100年
So what is his worth?
那麼到底他的價值是怎麼樣
So now in the US, UK, France, Canada
所以現在在美國 英國 法國 加拿大
So he's debating what the hell to do with this city ship
那麼他正在討論到底如何處理這條城船
Of course many commercial businessmen
當然很多commercial的商人
to salvage these things
去打撈這些東西
Because he has too many magical legends
因為他太多的神奇的傳說
So I want to fish for the treasures inside and sell them.
所以都想去捞里面的宝贝拿出来卖
do a business
做一个商业
But now in the United States they prevent such an act
可是现在的美国他们阻止这样一个行为
He believes that this is still a very important cultural heritage of human beings
他认为这是一个还是一个很重要的人类的一个文化的遗产
is a so-called memory
是一个所谓的一个memory
A very good historical memory of a human being
一个非常好的一个人类的历史记忆
So we still have to find a way to legislate to protect this city ship
所以还是要想办法立法要保护这条城船
so so why
那么所以因此呢
In fact, there are many cultural heritages of these human beings underwater.
水下其实是有很多的这些的人类的这些文化的遗留遗产
Many of them have very important historical or cultural values
其中有很多很多然然具有很重要的一些历史或者是文化的这一个价值
But why did we not do archaeology in the water in the past?
但是为什么过去我们不到水里的考古
The Pyramid we just saw
我们刚刚看到的Pyramid
Egyptian pyramids
埃及的金字塔
This Bi Meiying of Qin Shihuang
这个秦始皇的这个比玫瑩
There are many other kinds on land
还有很多各种各样的都在陆地上面
Why don't you go into the water and do archaeology?
为什么不去到水里面去做考古呢
right
对不对
In fact, you can't and you can't do it
其实是不能也非不为也
In fact, humans have known for a long time that there are many treasures in the water
其实人类很早就知道里面有很多宝贝在水里面
so he can't go down
所以他下不去
because you mainly
因为你主要
everyone because we know
大家由於我們知道
You hold your breath for two minutes and you're done.
你憋氣兩分鐘就完蛋了這樣子
So it's just not going down
所以只是下不去而已
In fact, human beings have been
其實人類自古呢
Just a wish to dive into the water
就到潛入水中的一個願望
look at this
你看這個
We have recorded in these ancient documents in China
我們在中國的這些古文獻裡面就記載
as early as when bluestone was yellow
早在青石黃的時候
He knew there was a roof in the water
他就知道水裡面有頂
Because the ancient Chinese especially the rulers
因為古代中國人尤其是統治者
Very important to this top
對這個頂非常看重的
able to get the top
能夠獲得頂
represents one of his powers
就代表他的一種權力
become a real man
變成一個真命天子
So he has the top of the Zhou Dynasty
所以他就是有周代的這個統頂
Of course you need to use Sishui Zhaozhao
當然要用到四水照照照
What about Emperor Wu of the Han Dynasty?
那麼漢武帝呢
his reign dome
他的年號圓頂
he tops for some favorites
他因為一些最愛的得頂
Divide the water
分水上
Got the top in this watershed
在這個分水裡面獲得了頂
so they know the water has a lot of
所以他們知道水裡面有很多
something from the past is in it
過去的一些東西在裡面
so they want to find
所以他們想要去找
What about the Greek philosopher?
那麼這個希臘的哲學家呢
What about Ariswold?
亞里斯沃德呢
They also know the water
他們他也知道水裡面
should go down and have a look
應該下去看一看
Why can't I go down?
怎麼下去下不去
can't we breathe in?
对不对 我们不能够呼吸吗进去
Immediately suffocated
马上就被憋死了
so he therefore
所以他因此呢
he is very smart
他很聪明
He spoke of man's ability to turn bronze chests
他讲到人类可以将青铜柜子
Put a bronze iron cabinet into the water
把一个青铜的铁柜子放到水里面去
Then people inside can go to the iron cabinet
然后里面人可以到铁柜子里面
It can use its residual air inside
里面可以利用它残余的空气
can come and dive into the water
可以来潜入到水里面
So this is a
所以这个是一个
These
这些
look at this
这个你看这个
Humans are missing from these two pictures from antiquity
人类从古代这两个照片不见了
I suddenly managed to go
我突然办法去了
that this
那这个
this from
这个从从
From before the festival
从那个祭仁前以前
Until Jingguo entered the Qian century
一直到景国入干世纪呢
Just trying to get into the water
就想办法要到水里面去
look at it this is fun
你看它这个很好玩
it uses this thing to put it inside
它用这个东西套到里面去
go into the water
到水里面去
This is also a cabinet
这也是用一个柜子
man inside through an air
人在里面的透过一个空气
then put the air in
然后就把空气进来
then dive
然后潜水
then this is more fun
然后这个更好玩了
he uses a bucket
他用一个桶子
people inside
人在里面
Do you see it
看到没有
Then this hand is outside
然后这手在外面
he can pick up things in it
他可以捡东西在里面
This is getting better and better
这个越来越慢慢进步了
have some strange ideas
有一些奇特的一些想法
into the water to dive
到水裡面去潛水
this is a
這個是一個
this one came out
這個出來了
This is at 900BC
這個是在900BC的時候
Humans want to use this method
人類想要用這個辦法
animal skin
用動物的皮囊
Then pipe it into the
然後用管子連接到裡面
it can see through the air of the skin
它可以透過皮囊的空氣
activities in the water
在水裡面活動
this is the same
這個也是一樣
You see it also uses the skin
你看它也利用皮囊
then in this
然後在這個
It's in this Middle East
這是在這個中東的一個
ancient mural above
古代的壁畫上面
accomplished
所成就
So what about the people at that time?
所以代表當時的人呢
He tried to get into the water
他想辦法要到水裡面去
to dive
要潛水
I'm going to have a look
要去看壹下
fished something
撈了撈東西
Fishing for antiquities
撈了撈古物
or go see some
或者去看壹些
some other things
其他的一些東西
then this thing
那麼這個東西
what about this wish
這個願望呢
By 1943
到了1943年
finally come true
終於都實現了
Anyone who knows how to dive now knows
我們現在如果會潛水的人都知道
It is very important that the water fee
很重要的就是這個水費
Now divers will carry this on their backs
那現在潛水人都會背著這個
It is what we usually call the water fee
就是我們壹般叫水費
it passes through an air
它透過壹個空氣
Oxygen level
也氧气平
Then pass through an air conditioner
然后通过一个空气的调节气
Then it can breathe in water
然后它可以在水里面呼吸
can move in water
可以在水里面活动
And this kind of activity can be done freely
而且可以自由自在的这种活动
So this is a very important invention
所以这个是一个很重要的一个发明
this is by a french
这个是由一个法国人
this is the one this is his name
就是这一位 这是他的名字
Jack Costow
Jack Costow
such a he is a naval officer
这样一个 他是海军军官
He invented the water bill
他发明了这个水费
So he realized this human
所以他实现了这一个人类
able to move underwater
可以在水下活动的
such a dream of diving
潜水的这样一个梦想
So this is what he invented
那么这个是当初他发明的
Such a water fee with two buckets
有两个这个桶子的这样的一个水费
Then the discovery of the water fee for this water
那么这个水的水费的发现
This human can go into the water
这个人类可以到水里去了
right
对不对
He can swim freely in the water
他可以很自由自在的在水里面
can stay for a while
可以待一段时间
can see what he wants to see
可以去看他所想要看的东西
wants to get what he wants
想要捞他所想要捞的东西
then this
那么这个
but this result
但是这个结果
first one of his effects
第一个他的一个效应
that humans can find in water
就是人类可以在水里面发现
some ancient cultures should
古代的一些文化应该
Including ships, buildings, ruins and ancient relics, etc.
包括成船 建筑物 遗址和古代文物等等
It is free to discover these things
它可以自由的去发现这些东西
But after discovering
但是发现之后呢
become another side effect?
变成另外一个副作用呢
Just started a treasure trove
就是兴起了一个捞宝
Everyone goes to the water to find treasure
大家都到水里去捞宝
Because everyone knows that there are many treasures in the water
因为大家知道水里面有很多的宝贝
So it has to go to the water to find treasure
所以它要到水里去捞宝
What about this loot?
那么这个捞宝呢
still a lot of people
一直到现在还是一个很多人
Still thinking of fishing for treasure
还是想到水里捞宝
that this is a recent event
那这个是一个最近发生的事情
that was in 2007
那个是在2007年
America's famous one in Furley
美国在Furley的一个很有名的一个
An ocean exploration company called Odyssey
叫做Odyssey的一个海洋探测公司
it's this it's a very strong company
那它的这个 它的非常强壮的一个公司
What about its biggest task?
那么它的最大的任务呢
Just go to sea to find these things
就是到海里去找这些东西
Probe, find these undersea safeguards
探测 去找这些海底的保障
So it was in 2007 when
所以它在2007年的时候
it's in this spanish in portuguese
它在这个西班牙 在葡萄牙的
What about the big sunset in the south?
南边的这个大夕阳里面呢
it found a boat
它就发现了一条成船
to detect an adult ship
来探测到一条成船
Then go down and do it
然后呢 下去去做
Lay it down
打牢
he hit the city ship
他打这个城船
He named himself Black Swan
他自己命名为叫Black Swan
black swan
就是黑天鹅
after black swan
黑天鹅后
Then this city ship is incredible
然后这个城船是不得了
what do you see because of him
因为他你看出的是什么
is a gold coin
是金币
right
对不对
gold
金币
how many gold coins are in it
它里面有多少金币
There are 500,000 gold coins
有50万个金币
then this
然后这个
how much does it add up to
加起来有多少重量
There are 17 tons
有17吨
So that's a big one-coin fortune
所以这是一个很大的一币财富
but it is
但是它是
caught in the Atlantic
在大西洋捞到的
But its wealth caused
但是它这个财富就引起了
Protests in Spain
西班牙的抗议
because spanish says
因为西班牙说
the boat
这条船
it's their boat
它是他们的这条船
called mercedes
叫Mercedes
this is what they are
这个是他们在
when the british fought
害英国作战的时候
a ship silent in the atlantic
沉默在大西洋的一条船
This ship is sailing back to Spain from South America
这个船是从南美洲航回到西班牙
Then there was silence in the middle
然后在中间就沉默了
so they want to ask
所以他们要要求
This thing has to be returned to the devil
这东西要归还鬼
Spain
西班牙
then this thing
那么这个事情
of course until now
当然到现在为止
no big lawsuit for it yet
还没有它的大官司
big lawsuit
大官司
during that period
那这期间
this peru
这个秘鲁
Miru is also asking why
密鲁也在要 为什么
He said you shipped this thing from Miru
他说你这个东西是从密鲁运出来的
Then you were not unified by our Miru people
那么你当时没有经过我们的密鲁人统一
You're shipped to Spain
你就运到了西班牙去了
Spain just said it's not okay
西班牙就说了 这不行
Because you were my colony at the time
因为你当时密鲁是我的殖民地
You are not a sovereign state yourself
你自己并不是一个主权国家
so you have no right to ask
所以你没有权利来要求
So now the lawsuit is still going on
所以现在官司还在打
This also involves American diplomacy and politics
这个也涉及到美国的外交和政治
Because the US government is supporting Spain
因为美国政府是支持西班牙
But this Audis company
但是这个Audis公司
He is a very powerful private
他是非常有势力的一个私人
he is very powerful
他很有势力的人
so he found a lot of lawyers
所以他找到很多律师
then think american
然后认为美国人
Why don't you favor us Americans
你怎么不偏谈我们美国人
to support Spain
要去支持西班牙的
So he thinks these American governments are a conspiracy
所以他认为这些美国政府是一个阴谋
because of what
因为什么
Because the US government wants to get a painting back from Spain
因为美国政府想要从西班牙拿回一幅画
an ancient painting
一幅古代的画
so make an exchange
所以做一个交换
So it's in the middle so far
所以是中间到目前为止还在
Some lawsuits are still pending
有一些官司还没有了 还在打
So this also shows
所以这也说明了
In fact underwater he is one of many of these ancient safeguards
其实水下他是一个很多的这些古代的保障
So actually until now
所以其实一直到现在
everyone still wants
大家还想要
He wanted to catch these ancient humans in the water
他想到水里去捞这些古代人类
legacy safeguards
所遗留的这些保障
so this thing has a lot of
所以这东西有很多的
until now
一直到现在
What I said is that we still have them in Taiwan.
我说的还是到现在我们台湾的还是有
many people who can dive
很多会潜水的人
He wanted to fish for some ancient porcelain from the bottom of the sea
他想到海底去捞一些古代的磁器
can be exchanged for money
可以拿出来换成金钱
So this has aroused some people's attention
所以这个就引起了一些大家的重视
because of this
因为这样子的话
Although there are many of these under the sea
海下的这些虽然很多
But after these people kept going down to salvage
但是这些人不断地下去打捞之后
These things will all come to naught
这些东西都会化为乌有了
They were all taken away by individuals
都被个人去拿走了
so therefore
所以因此
The country I visited feels
这个游的国家就觉得
we should make some laws
我们应该定一些法令
to protect these underwater
来保护这些水下的
so-called cultural heritage
所谓的文化的遗产
Then the UK first in 1973
那么英国首先在1973年
That's 30 years after the water bill was invented in 1943
这就是在水费1943年发明之后的30年
At the beginning, the United Kingdom established this traditional protection law
开始英国定定了这个陈传保护法
Just to protect these Chen Chuan
就是保护这些陈传
Then his Chen Chuan
那么他这个陈传
According to Chen Chuan's historical archaeological and artistic value
根据陈传的历史考古和艺术价值
then want to specify
然后想要来指定
After the designation, the government will have power
指定之后政府就要去有权力
to protect it
去保护它
That is
那就是
that thing
那这个东西
Well
呃
then this
然后这个
By 1982
到了1982年
What about the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea?
这个联合国的海洋法公约呢
He also started to define this, this, this clause
他也开始定定了这个这个这个条文
It is to require that the protection of sea discoveries has cultural asset value
就是要求这个保护海上发现具有文化资产价值
and items of historical value
和历史价值的物品
it was 1982
那这是1982年
The United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea
这个联合国的海洋法公约里面
Also set such a
也定出这样的一个
uh a law
呃一个法条
then 1988
然后1988年
the International Law Association
这个国际法协会
ah
啊
What about the IRA?
这个IRA呢
He also started noticing the problem
他也开始注意到这个问题
So he also planned to fry a draft convention on underwater cultural assets
所以他也擬炒了一个水下文化资产公约草案
he is the draft
他是这个草案而已
ah
啊
a draft
一个草案
But it didn't turn into a formal
但是并没有后来变成一个正式的
a law
一个法条
Then in 1990
然后到了1990年
This international stock machine and a group of federations
这个国际股机与一组联会
This one is at Ecmo in Rome, Italy
这个是在意大利罗马的Ecmo
Well he uh
那么他呃
in 1996
在1996年的时候呢
He also passed a current chapter called the Management of Underwater Cultural Assets Conservation
他也通过了一个叫水下文化资产保护管理现章
Charter on the protection and management of
Charter on the protection and management of
and the water culture heritage
and the water culture heritage
then this is a
那麼這是一個
in 1990
1990年的時候呢
There is a formal
有正式的
There is such an international
有這麼一個國際性的
protection of underwater heritage
保護水下遺產的
such a chatter
這樣一個chatter
Then in 2001
然後到了2001年
Finally our United Nations
最後我們這聯合國
He is passing a called
他就在通過了一個叫做
I
我
The UNESCO of the United Nations
這個聯合國的UNESCO
UNESCO
叫科文組織
Convention on the Protection of the Underwater Cultural Heritage
保護水下文化遺產公約
So this is enough to see
所以這個足為一看得到
What about this underwater?
這個水下呢
Actually very late
其實非常的晚的
until recently
一直到最近
you see the 21st century
你看到了21世紀了
and then slowly
然後才開始慢慢的
everyone should pay attention
大家要注意到
to protect these underwater
去保護這些水下的
these human heritage
這些人類的遺產
the unesco convention
這個科文組織公約
After this mud
這個草泥之後呢
Many countries cannot be consecutive
很多的國家不可能連續
because it must have
因為它一定要有
After 20 countries in a row
20個國家連續之後呢
This agreement will come into force
這個公約才會生效
why
為什麼呢
because like many countries
因為像很多國家
for self benefit
為了自身的利益
like just america
像剛剛美國
The United States and other countries have many large consortia
美國它的國家有很多大的財團
Specially on stage
專門在台上這塊
after the treaty of interest
利益的公約之後呢
it's over
它就完蛋了
So the U.S. government has never dared to sign this
所以美國政府始終就不敢簽這個
dare not sign
不敢簽簽署
That's why I haven't been able to make up enough
那這個所以一直都湊不足
Not enough to make up the number of this country
湊不足這個國家的數目
until January 2009
一直到2009年1月
barely enough
才勉強湊足了
has just come into effect
才開始正式的生效
So now every country in the world
所以現在全世界的每一個國家
It wants to protect its underwater cultural heritage
它要保護它的水下的文化遺產
must be subject to this convention
都必須要以這個公約
as a basis for it
來作為它的一個基礎
So so according to this convention
那麼所以根據這個公約
So our underwater cultural heritage
那麼我們水下的文化遺產
What is probably the cultural heritage of hydration
大概是什麼是水化的文化遺產
it has a definition
它有一個定義
Then he said underwater cultural heritage
那麼他說水下文化遺產
it is partially or fully underwater
它是部分或全部位於水下
periodic or continuous existence
周期性的或連續性的存在
at least 100 years
至少100年
Just 100 years ago
就100年的這個年代
At the same time it has contained content that contains
同時它有包含的內容是包含
Refers to building houses, handicrafts
以指建築房屋、工藝品
human remains
人類的遺骸
and its archaeological and natural drama
以及其考古和自然的戲落
The second is ships, aircraft
第二個是船隻、飛行器
and other means of transport
和其他運輸工具
or any part of the above three categories
或上述三類的任何部分
goods or other items
所在貨物或其他物品
archaeological and natural drama
及考古自然戲落
prehistoric animals
具有史前易動物
Then this is in the underwater heritage protection apartment of the United Nations
那这个是联合国的这个水下遗产保护公寓里面
What are these defined underwater heritage
所界定的这些什么叫的水下遗产
Of course, like the cables we often use in our oceans now
当然像现在我们海里面常常的电缆
Some of these seabeds are still used
仍然使用的这些海底的一些
Like the earthquake predictor we recently deployed off the coast of Yinan
像我们最近在宜南外海放的地震预测器
Of course this doesn't count because it's modern.
这个当然都不算 因为是近代的
So in the past, if there were 100 years
那么过去凡是有100年的时间
These things probably need to be protected.
这些东西大概都是需要保护的
the heritage of these cultures
这些的文化的遗产
Well, in this 100 years, there have been new political theories recently
那么可是这个100年最近也有新的政论
Especially just saw Katanic
特别是刚刚看到Katanic
After many people on the Katani went fishing
Katani号的这个很多人去了捞之后
Now it needs to be changed to a later date, about 50 years
现在要改成更晚进大概到50年
can have the heritage of these cultures that need to be protected
就可以具有这个需要保护的这些文化的遗产
Well, the invention of the water fee except this
那么这个水费的发明除了这个
About fishing insurance involving underwater
关于涉及到水下的捞保
In addition to the protection of underwater cultural heritage?
还有水下文化遗产的保护之外呢
What about another effect?
另外一个产生的一个效果呢
It is this archaeology that has emerged as a new field
就是这个考古学出现了一个新的领域
Because archeology in the past was all on land
因为过去的考古学都是在陆地上面的
Archaeologists dig with shovels
考古家是拿铲子要挖的
But now archaeologists need to go into the water
但是現在的考古學家需要到水裡面去了
That's why it's called underwater archaeology.
所以才算是水下考古學
Well, underwater archeology didn't really appear until the 1960s.
那水下考古學是在1960年代才正式出現
This is an American archaeologist named George Bath
這是一個美國的考古學家叫George Bath
Well he's retired now
那麼他現在已經退休了
He is a professor at the University of Texas AMM in the United States
他是美國的Texas AMM的大學的教授
then he retired
那麼他退休了
I kept in touch with him until recently
我一直到最近我還給他保持一些聯絡
He is considered the father of underwater archaeology
他是認為是水下考古學之父
a founder
一個founder
Well, he's first in the Turkish waters on the south side
那麼他首先在土耳其海域在南邊的這邊
called Cabidonia for underwater surveys
叫做Cabidonia這個地方來進行水下的調查
He's investigating East Rome
他所調查的是東羅馬
These are the city legends of the Byzantine period
就是拜占庭時期的這些城傳
Discover a wealth of these cultural relics from the Byzantine era
發現大量的這些拜占庭時代的文化遺留
So for us to understand these Byzantine eras from the Eastern Roman era
所以對於我們了解東羅馬時代的這些拜占庭時代的
The traffic of these past seas
這些過去的海上的交通
The production of these trades at the time
這些貿易當時的生產
Korean technology and so on
韓技术等等呢
He provided some important
他提供了很重要的一些
some new information
新的一些訊息
So this is considered a very important one
所以這個被認為是非常重要的一個
A job in underwater archeology
水下考古的一個工作
then this
那麼這個
This is where he was at the time
這個是他當時在這邊這個
south coast of Türkiye
土耳其的南邊的海域
The archaeological work carried out
所進行的這些考古工作
he is totally one
他完全是一個
Here's what he collected for research
這是他所蒐集的做調查的
This map of this MAP
這個MAP的這個地圖
look at these wrecks found
你看這些發現的沉船
So wait a minute
所以一物等等啊
Well, he is using a very scientific method
那麼他是利用一個非常科學的方法
to carry out underwater
來進行水下的
instead of big fish
而不是大撈
He is an underwater archaeologist
他是一個水下的考古學
that is very systematic
那個很有系統的
From a scientific point of view?
以科學性的這個角度呢
to carry out underwater cultural relics?
來進行水下的文物呢
to collect
來進行採集
record
進行記錄
to investigate
進行調查
so so
那麼所以
Now we get into this underwater archeology
現在我們就進入到這個水下的這個考古學
Because of this, after all, Taiwan has not
因為這個畢竟他們台灣過去還沒有
so i thought i would like to slightly
所以我想我想稍微
can introduce
可以介紹一下
What is underwater archaeology?
所謂什麼叫水下考古學
It's actually archaeology
其实它就是考古学
It basically its principles and some of its methods
它基本上它的原则和它的一些方法
basically the same as archeology
基本上是和考古学是一样的
But some of its tools use
但是它的一些使用的工具
the equipment it uses
它所使用的设备
Of course, the environment of archaeology on the road is different.
那就和路上考古学当然环境不一样
So therefore it's not the same as this
所以因此它的这个也不一样
So underwater archeology it's all about combining diving equipment
所以水下考古学它就是要结合潜水装备
and Ocean Exploration Technology
和海洋探测科技
By investigating and discovering
借由调查与发掘
Submerged ship ruins and relics, etc.
淹没在水下的船只遗迹与遗物等
To study the history and culture of human beings in the past
来研究过去的人类的历史文化
So it's going to combine diving
所以它要结合的潜水
and some marine exploration equipment
还有一些海洋探测设备
and other disciplines
还有其他的一些学科
Come and do these underwater
来一起来做这些水下
Relic and ship detection work
遗迹遗物的和船只的探测的工作
job found
发现的工作
So so as an underwater archaeologist
那么所以作为一个水下考古学家
It's more complicated than this terrestrial archeology
它要比这个陆地考古学更为的复杂
It's road archeology is already complicated
它是路上考古学已经很复杂了
But underwater archeology
但是水下考古学
The environment in which it works is inside the water
它涉及的它工作的环境在水里面
so it's more complicated
所以它更为复杂
it has to be a team job
它必须是团队的工作
so it includes more than just archaeologists
所以它包含了不只是考古学家
Ocean explorer Marine engineer Historian Marine geologist
海洋探測學家 海洋工程學家 歷史學家 海洋地質學家
Ancient tomb maintenance scientists, communication personnel, diving workers, etc.
古墓維護學家 還有傳播的人員以及潛水工作者等等
It is a teamwork, not a job that any individual can perform
它是一個teamwork 不是任何一個個別可以來執行的一項工作
This picture is a typical underwater archaeological work
這張圖就是一個典型的水下考古的工作
You see there must be a working platform above the water
你看上面要有水上工作平台 下面這些要一起潛水人員
If the following archaeological excavations are carried out,
下面假如進行考古的發掘的時候
So it still has to follow the archaeological method
所以它必須還是要依照考古學的方法
Some principles to do these archaeological work
一些原則來做這些考古的工作
Then all these unearthed cultural relics
然後這些所有的出土的文物
It must be transported to the sea in a welfare bag like a welfare bag
它必須要再用福利袋 像福利袋的運到海面上去
it's a part job
這是一個一部分的工作
Then go back and there are some unearthed cultural relics and some maintenance
然後回去還有一些出土文物的一些維護的
Because the preservation environment of underwater cultural relics is very different from that on the road
因為水下文物它是保存環境和路上面有很大的差別
Regardless of the water pressure, regardless of the environment of the water body
不管是水壓 不管是水體的環境
basically very different
基本上非常不一樣的
So once things come out of the water
所以东西一出水之后呢
to be maintained immediately
要立刻加以维护
Otherwise it will be destroyed immediately
否则立刻就毁坏掉了
so therefore
所以因此呢
This artifact is preserved in Underwater Archeology
这个文物维护在水下考古学里面
is also a very important part
也是一个很重要的一个部分
so so so
那么所以说因此呢
What about underwater archaeology?
水下考古学呢
It does more than just discover shipwrecks
它研究的不只是发现沉船
or pick up the items
或取其中的货品
Instead, we need to use the context of underwater archaeological data
而是要借由水下考古资料的脉络
To study the human cultural legacy related to the ocean
来研究与海洋有关的人类文化遗留
including social economy political religion
包括社会 经济 政治 宗教
Legacy at various levels
各种层面遗留
and its environmental factors
以及它所存在的环境因素
It's an underwater archeology
这是一个水下考古学
So what about underwater archaeology?
所以因此水下考古学呢
it is very important
它是非常的重要的
It is important in several ways
它重要有几个方面
The first is of course an important cultural
第一个是当然是一个重要文化
What about underwater cultural relics?
水下的文化遗存呢
It has quite a few assets that are an important cultural
它有相当多是一个重要的文化的资产
why
为什么呢
Because these things are in the sea
因为这些东西在海里面呢
It is a flotant
它就是一个被flotant的
also by a frozen wave of time
也被一个冻结的一个时间的浇浪
Everything stops at that time
所有的东西就停格在它那个时间
so anything in it
所以它里面任何的东西呢
it can reflect
它可以反映出来
All the real conditions at that time
在那一個時間上的所有當時的一些真實的狀況
So therefore it is a very important cultural asset
所以因此它是一個很重要的一個文化資產
At the same time, it certainly has very important academic research value
同時它也當然具有很重要的學術研究的價值
Because underwater remains often provide us with a lot in our archives
因為水下的遺存它往往提供給我們很多在我們的文獻檔案裡面
Some new information that was not there
所沒有的一些新的訊息
These messages may not be in any mean documentation file
這些訊息也許並不介於任何的意思文獻檔案
But it can exist in the remains of these substances unearthed from underwater
但是它可以存在於從水下所出土的這些物質的遺留裡面
Can tell us a lot of various information
可以告訴我們很多的各種各樣的一些訊息
Including the agreement of the individual to that of the whole group
包括個人的一致到底整個團體的
or from something tiny to a large group itself
或者從一些微小的東西到一個大的團體本身
These engineering techniques and so on
這些工程技術等等
And the development of the entire history of human culture
還有整個的人文化史的發展
It can often provide some very important information
它都往往可以提供很重要的一些訊息
In addition, of course, the underwater cultural heritage is now
另外當然水下文化遺產在現在
It is also a very important tourist resource.
也也是一個很重要的一個觀光資源
So now many countries are also developing underwater museums
所以現在很多國家也在發展水下博物館
Like this mainland-like Three Gorges in Egypt
像這個在埃及的像大陸的三峽
after it was flooded by the reservoir
它被水庫淹起來之後
Some are in the water and it builds an underwater museum
有的在水裡它建立一個水下的博物館
You can also go to the water to see
也可以到水裡面去看
so it can attract a lot of these tourists
所以它就可以吸引大量的這些觀光客
Now also advocate this so-called diving tourism
現在也倡導這個所謂潛水觀光
There are some city ships that allow spectators to allow tourists to approach
有一些城船可以讓觀眾可以讓遊客去接近的
you can go snorkeling at home
可以你家裡去浮潛
Or diving can come close to these underwater
或者說潛水可以來接近這些水下的
The remains of these fascinating ancient cultures
這些具有吸引力的古代文化的遺留
It has also become a very important tourist resource
它也變成一個非常重要的觀光資源
like our yap island in the pacific
像我們在太平洋的亞普島
Saipan in the Taipei Ocean
台北洋的塞班島
These all look like this
這些都有這樣子
These are very economically beneficial
這些非常可以產生很多經濟效益的
such a benefit
這樣的一個效益
I thought I'd give a quick introduction to underwater archeology
我想我很快地介紹一下水下考古學
Underwater archaeology is actually the same method as land archaeology
水下考古學其實它的方法和陸地考古學是一樣的
It also includes the collection of research information for the project
它也包含計畫的研擬資訊的蒐集
Underwater archaeological investigation and excavation
水下考古調查發掘
Finally, there is maintenance and placement of water cultural relics
最後還有出水文物的維護安置
Also research interpretation presentation and publication
還有研究解釋展示和出版
Then this is as an underwater archeology
那這個是作為一個水下考古
Underwater archeology requires a very careful planning
水下考古它是要做一個非常整密的規劃
These plans include its scope of purpose
這些規劃包含它的目的範疇
Tactics, methods, cost of personnel, equipment, and laws
策略方法 實成人員經費 裝備以及法律
because it is a cultural asset
因為它是一個文化資產
After entering, the water must comply with the legal norms
進去之後 水裡面一定要符合法律的規範
In addition, there is actually an ecological
另外其實還有一個生態
Because underwater work cannot damage the existing underwater ecological environment
因為水下的工作也不能夠破壞到水下既有的生態環境
So these things have to go through a very careful planning
所以這些東西都是要經過一個很整密的規劃
to be able to execute
才能夠來執行
So our regulations are quite strict
所以我們的法規也規定的相當嚴格
Now Taiwan we are firing you
現在台灣我們正在炒你一個
Underwater Cultural Assets Preservation Act
水下文化資產保存法
This file will already fire one of your bills
這個文件會已經炒你的一個法案
Currently still in the Executive Yuan
現在目前還在行政院
After the Executive Yuan passed it, it was called Soli Court
我行政院通過之後叫索利法院
and then pass
然後再通過
So this is the collection of information
那麼這個是資訊的收集
Well, underwater archeology is not just about going underwater.
那麼作為水下考古並不是逛到水下去而已
Actually it requires a lot of related work
其實它需要很多相關的工作
So it's a fairly labor-intensive
所以它是一個相當花費人力時間的
it needs to be dictated
它這個需要有口述的
Because many underwater messages are not necessarily given the file
因為很多的水下的訊息不見得鑑於文件
Oral data instead
那麼反而是口述資料
can tell us a lot about this
可以告诉我们很多的这方面的讯息
So local fishermen are like sailors
所以当地渔民像行船的人
This kind of sailors, etc.
这种开船的人这些等等
They will have a lot of information
他们都会有很多的一些讯息
Come tell us about the underwater
来告诉我们水下的一些
what they met i saw
他们所碰到的我见到的
some underwater remnants of some culture
一些水下的一些文化的遗留
like especially fishermen
像特别是渔民
he sometimes trawls
他有时候拖网
Or he, a fisherman's reconnaissance machine
或者他这个渔民的余探机
You will find a lot of underwater
会发现到水下很多的一些
Target
目标物Target
Then he will record again
然后他又会记录起来
especially some shipwrecks
特别是一些沉船
because he often trawls
因为他往往拖网的时候
broke his net
就把他的网拖破掉了
So fishermen hate the entrance
所以渔民就恨之入口
hate very much
非常恨
So he'll just jot that down
所以他就会把那个点就记下来
So the next time he goes
所以他下次去的时候
don't go past that point
不要经过那个点
These points are often second to us
这些点往往对于我们二言
becomes an important
就变成一个很重要的
valuable information
宝贵的讯息
because he told you there's something over there
因为他告诉你那边有东西
he may be a shipwreck
他也许是沉船
maybe a big rock
也许是一个大的岩石
But at least it's a potential target
但是至少它是一个潜在的一个目标物
Also some food information
另外有一些食物资料
This information contains archaeological information on these roads
这个资料包含这些路上考古的资料
because the boat is in the sea
因为船在海里面
Tend to be affected by the waves will be affected by some factors
往往会被海浪会被一些因素
Will bring some parts to land
会把一些部分东西带到陆地上去了
There will be some ancient porcelain on the coast
在海岸边会有一些古代的磁器
or something on board
或者一些船上的物品
these things are some clues
这些东西都是一些线索
So when we investigated Pongpo
所以我们在蓬浦调查的时候
These porcelains from the Yuan Dynasty can be found at the seaside
在海边就可以发现到送代元代的这些磁器
Tell us there must be these wrecks nearby
告诉我们附近一定有这些沉船
These shipwrecks are the ones we haven't found yet.
这些沉船就是我们还没有找到
Or the past has been washed away by the waves
或者过去已经被海浪冲了不见了
then this is a
那么这个是一个
In addition, of course, the information of Wenwen County is still very important.
另外当然文文县资料还是很重要的
We're going to start with some files
我们要从一些檔案
Find some clues from some historical documents
从一些历史文献里面来找一些线索
In addition, the geographical environment
另外就是地理环境
Because of these places where the shipwreck
因为沉船的这些所在
It is related to the geographical environment
它和地理环境它是有关系的
near these are mountain peppers
这些附近有山胡椒
There is a diving beach
有潜滩
Hazardous glue
有险胶
these things
这些东西
There are still very fluid in these environments
这些环境里面还有很流的
strong current
很激的水流
Ocean currents can cause these shipwrecks
海流都是可以造成这些沉船的
produced by a place
所产生的一个地方
So these data are very important to us
所以这些资料我们都是很重要的
Then this as a look
那这个作为看
This is after we use various information
这个是我们利用各种的一些讯息之后
Like our investigation in Penghu
像我们在澎湖做调查
Let's temporarily locate these possible potentials
我们就先暂时locate这些可能的一些potential的
some possible locations
一些可能的一些地点
Potential existence and existence
有潜在可能性的存在与存传
or this location of the submerged target
或者是潜水下目标物的这个地点
Then we are going to use this information
那么下面我们就是要根据这些讯息
To do this underwater credible survey
要做这个水下的靠谱调查
investigation
调查
vast sea
茫茫大海
That needle in the haystack
那大海捞针
We can't go to all the oceans
我们不可能去所有的海域呢
do the research
都去做调查
go to sea as a sister
作为妹到海里去
When you go into the sea, you feel like a tree in the ocean
你到海里去自己觉得算沧海之一树
to the vast sea
到海里茫茫大海
My home is too small
自己家里面太渺小了
then you have to do the research
那你要去做调查
how to do the investigation
怎么做调查呢
right
对不对
Of course we're fine now
那当然我们现在还好
good technology now
现在有很好的科技
So this underwater archaeological team
所以这个一个水下的考古团队
We'll include these experts in ocean exploration
我们会包含这一些海洋探测的这些专家
Instruments that help exploit these detections
帮助利用这些探测的仪器
to help us discover some possible
来帮助我们去发现一些可能的
some potential targets
一些潜在的一些目标物
Now our most commonly used is SizeGain
現在我們最常用的是SizeGain
SizeGain Zona
SizeGain Zona
Scanning Sodium
測掃聲鈉
it uses a sound wave
它是利用一個聲波
This sonic instrument
這種聲波儀器
Come hit the ship from that
來從那個打到海船上面
and then reflect back
然後再反射回來
look at this sonic
看這個聲波的
to sonic
去進行聲波的
Then found that there may be some
然後發現底下可能有一些
this target
這個目標物
Another sound measurement system called polysonic
另外一個叫做多音速的測聲系統
Called MatiBing System
叫MatiBing System
This is called the sound measuring system
這個叫做測聲系統
This is also a principle of using a sound wave
這也是利用一種聲波的一個原理
Of course it can find
當然它可以發現到
Some of the following possible targets
下面的一些可能存在的一些目標物
In addition, this Strata Instant Noodle Apparatus
另外這個地層泡面儀
叫Subbutton Provider
叫Subbutton Provider
This Stratum Instant Noodle Apparatus uses this
這個地層泡面儀就是利用這個
use the seabed above
用海床上面
Many of them were buried by the seabed and sea sand.
很多的被海床海沙都淹埋了
You only rely on these two instruments in front of you
你光靠這個前面這兩種儀器
dare not find it
不敢發現它
Because it's buried at a meter two meters
因為它被埋在一公尺兩公尺
In the mud three meters below
三公尺底下的泥巴裡面
Therefore, you can use this Strata Instant Noodle Apparatus
所以因此可以利用這個地層泡面儀
can go deeper
可以更深入地進去
to discover what's buried beneath the seabed
來發現淹埋在海床下面的
possible target
這可能的目標物
Unmanned remote control front distance
無人遙控前距
There's something this pretty deep
有一些這個蠻深的地方
People still can't get down
人還不見得下得去
At this time we can use this so-called ROV
這個時候我們可以利用這個所謂ROV
Can use remote control
可以用遙控的
It's like a robot
等於是一個機器人
You can remotely control the robot to do photography in the water
可以遙控機器人到水裡去做攝影
Now there is a more advanced
現在還有一個更進步的
unmanned underwater vehicle
是用無人水像潛航機
This is remote control
這個是用遙控的
This doesn't even need a remote
這個更不需要遙控
just a robot
就是一個機器人
After entering, he can go by himself
進去以後他自己可以去
to take pictures
來照相
so like that titanic
所以像那個鐵達尼號
Basically use such a device
基本上都是利用這樣的一器
Go in and shoot to a depth of 3,000 meters
進去拍攝到3000公尺深的
Some of the current status of the Titanic
現在目前的鐵達尼號的一些現況
There is also a magnetometer
另外還有磁力儀
This magnetometer is used
這磁力儀是利用
Targets mainly for these metals
主要針對這些金屬類的目標物
to detect
來進行探測
Let's see the abnormal condition of its magnetism
來看它的磁力的異常的狀況
to speculate that there may be targets in the ground
來推測地下可能存在有目標物
So these we can use the underwater positioning system
所以這些我們可以利用水中定位系統
and Differential Global Positioning System
以及差分全球式定位系統
to define its scope
來定它的範圍
this target
這個目標物
Then this is the instrument we use when we work
那這個就是我們工作的時候所用的儀器
What about this part, our Academia Sinica team
那這個部分呢我們中研院團隊
we have some instruments
我們有一部分儀器
What about the other part of the instrument?
另外一部分儀器呢
Also with Sun Yat-Sen University School of Ocean Sciences
也和中山大學海洋科學院
We have a combination of a team
我們有一個合組一個team
let's do it together
我們一起來做
Like this is Mati Bing
像這個是Mati Bing
This is Chief Executive Shengna
這個是特首生娜
This is this Bud, Subbottom Profiler
這是這個Bud, Subbottom Profiler
This is the ROV, the unmanned submersible
這是ROV,無人潛水器
So this basically looks like this
那麼這個基本上就是這樣子
We towed the instruments behind the boat
我們把儀器拖在船後面
and then trace
然後進行上描
Let the above description be very systematic
讓上描是很有系統的
do this
來做這個
So what is more advanced now is to use this
那麼現在更進步的是用這個
Someone
有人的
A small submarine like this one can be built by a human
人可以做到裡面的這種小潛艇
Of course it's a pity we don't have this in Taiwan
當然很可惜我們台灣沒有這個
then in the future
那麼將來
when really needed
真正有需要的時候
maybe we hope
也許我們希望
Of course it's expensive and expensive
當然很貴,很花錢的
that part
那這個部分
There is no such
目前還沒有這個
Then when we do the investigation next time
那下面這個時候我們做調查的時候
Is it a random investigation?
是並不是亂調查
we are still very systematic
我們還是非常有系統
Formed into these grades, these Fangke systems
化成这些grade 这些方科系统
What can we do with this Fangke system?
我们可以利用这个方科系统呢
to do this sampling
来做这个抽样
We can't do it everywhere
我们不可能做每一个地方都做
We can do some sampling in the future
我们将来可以做一些抽样
do it do it do the research
来做 来做 来做调查
Then the other is us
那么另外就是我们
after discovery
发现之后呢
After the discovery of this series
这一系发现之后呢
We still have to go down by our dive source
我们还是要靠我们的潜水源下去
Why
为什么
Computers are still inferior to human brains
电脑还是不如人脑
right
对不对
the computer will tell you
那电脑就告诉你
There's a target down here
这边底下有个目标
but what is the target
但是目标是什么东西
it won't tell you
它不会告诉你
It just says there is an anomaly
它只是说有一个anomaly
There is something abnormal and a signal appears
有一些不正常的一个讯号出现
then maybe a
那么也许是一个
a rock
一块岩石
maybe a shipwreck
也许是一条沉船
maybe a city wall
也许是一个城墙
This thing must rely on our divers
这个东西必须要靠我们的divers
go down and search
去下去搜寻
It also needs to be very systematic.
下去它也是要很有系统的呢
to conduct a survey like this
来进行这样子的调查
It's not just wandering around the bottom
不是随便在底下乱游一通
then this is
那么这个是
So there are various ways of investigating this
所以这个有各种不同的调查的方式
including emergent
包括涌现式的
like a linear
像一个直线式的
These diving sources have been lined up
这些潜水源源一直排开
such investigation or
这样调查或者是
is corridor style
是走廊式的
Each person is responsible for a Cathedral and a corridor
每個人負責一個Cathedral 一個走廊
Or everyone in a circle
或者是大家在一個圓圈裡面
Playing circles to do surveys
玩的圓圈來做調查
There is a set of methods
這都是有一套的方法
In addition we investigate
另外我們做調查
Very important is this aerial and satellite photography
很重要的就是這個航空和衛星照相
Some of the information provided to us
所提供給我們的一些訊息
Now this technology is also very advanced
現在這個科技也非常進步
Nearest Central University
最近中央大學
They also want to take advantage of this
他們也想要利用這個
their space instruments
他們太空的儀器
to use the temperature
來利用溫度
Let's see if there are any unusual shipwrecks down there.
來看底下有沒有異常的這些沉船
Or these messages from underwater beings
或者是水底存在物的這些訊息
They are also experimenting with this part
這個部分他們也在做實驗
like this is
像這個是
This is in the Dongsha Islands
這個是在東沙群島的
Above Dongsha Atoll
東沙環礁上面
With this artificial satellite, you can image
用這個人造衛星上面就可以影像
It can be seen that in the shallow sea part
就看得出來在淺海部分的
there are many, many of these
所存在的很多很多的這些
The possible existence of this shipwreck
可能存在的這個沉船